I can try why'd you give you both the
Federal Reserve is hot you interested
right here with collateral American is
really handy printed thanks we'll have
the biggest fiscal stimulus we have ever
seen we are in the midst of a serious
financial crisis the government is
responding with decisive action we
competency have you taken a large home
loan or did you put your savings in
stocks mutual funds or bonds if not then
you can relax but all of us who did are
living on borrowed time
this is the story of the greatest
financial crisis of our time the one
that is on its way
[Music]
they spent hundreds of billions of
dollars to show that they were doing
something but not properly designed and
not as effective as its children when
they start losing money hey we got to
get back in the game we got to get those
dice rolling again
hey let's create another bubble you see
the dot-com boom we got a bigger one
welcome to real estate and they're ready
well the problem is they never actually
cure the crisis right they just give
alcohol to a drunk
it doesn't sober them up it just you
know sets them up for you know a bigger
hangover and that's all we've done and
that's all we're trying to do and so I
know at some point you kill the patient
at some point you can't drink anymore
it's just it's at the end of it we you
you reach the end of the ability and
that's where we go Congress wanted to
believe them Congress wanted an excuse
to bail out the auto workers and the
executives gave them just enough
political cover to say ah well I'm not
really doing this because I want auto
worker votes and I'm going to give them
a huge amount of money I'm really doing
this for the American economy
[Applause]
[Music]
so the solution is the problem that's
why we had a problem in the first place
this is the danger and protecting
investors and consumers from the
consequences of their own decisions
[Music]
we can do but we need to do it soon
because the clock is ticking and time is
not working in our favor I know many
Americans have questions tonight how did
we reach this point in our economy and
what does this mean for your financial
future these are good questions and they
deserve clear answers and they deserve
clear answers
they took down the symbols the financial
symbols of America the twin towers of
the world trade
today we had a national treasure
two airplanes have crashed people World
Trade Center
my my old company my whole company my
old company I used to work the whole
company is missing the story of the
great financial crisis begins just like
many of the stories of our era in the
United States on September 11 2001 the
terrorists knew exactly what they were
doing striking at the ultimate symbol of
the global economy and they did it when
the US was already slumping into a
recession after the.com bubble had burst
despite the tragic events of September
the 11th the foundations of our free
society remain sound and I'm confident
that we will recover and prosper as we
have in the past in spring 2001 the
Federal Reserve started lowering
interest rates and now it continued
lowering rates to save companies on the
brink and to keep unemployment down
during 2001 the interest rate was
lowered from 6.5 to 1.75 percent in 2003
it was cut all the way to 1 percent and
it remained there for a full year
predicting the panic of the way the
economic 9/11 and the current economic
crisis that were still in was probably
one of the easiest forecasts we've ever
made in our 30 years of trend
forecasting it was very simple gerald
Celente lives in kingston a few miles
north of new york
he's one of the top trend analysts in
the US he has been called the modern
Nostradamus
he didn't just predict the current
crisis he also predicted the dot-com
bubble and the stock market collapse of
1987 immediately after 9/11 the
president the United States george w
bush told the people to be good
Americans and go out and shop but how
are they going to do it you're in a
recession Federal Reserve comes to the
rescue in his memoir Federal Reserve
Chairman Alan Greenspan writes that he
knew that low interest rates might cause
a bubble traditionally central banks
remove the punch bowl once the party
stops the interest rate can't remain low
for too long or people will do things
they regret later this is one party they
just have to turn out right well the
purpose of a party is to have fun
together and the successful party needs
planning and skill Greenspan argue that
the Fed should never remove the punch
bowl but rather keep refilling it when
the party started to peter out
and if things went bad the Fed would
clean up the mess and tend to the hangul
banks and speculators loved it now they
could take greater risks than ever
before if they were successful they
could keep the profits and if they were
unlucky Greenspan would rescue normals
that way let me come home crying over
something and she'd give me candy every
time when you see the stock market come
down and the real estate bubble bursts
all that phony wealth is going to
evaporate and all that's going to be
left is all the debt that we accumulated
to foreigners
Peter Schiff is another analyst who was
roundly mocked when he predicted a
crisis for the US economy in the midst
of the boom we went on a unprecedented
global spending binge American citizens
borrowed and spent trillions of dollars
to buy stuff and that is why we're in so
much trouble it was because we got drunk
on all that fed alcohol that album in a
world that was subtly uncertain with a
country under attack nothing felt safer
than investing in your own home in the
American dream I do believe in the
American Dream I believe there is such a
thing as the American Dream owning a
home is a part of that drink just as
right here in America if you own your
own home are you realizing the American
dream Vernon Smith was awarded the Nobel
Prize in Economics in 2002 he received
it for his research in experimental
economics in his experiments he puts
economic theories to the test Smith is
an expert on bubbles if you can buy a
home with almost nothing down then you
do well if the prices continue to go up
if it goes down wasn't you you have an
incentive to walk away from and let the
bank have it low interest rates cost a
housing bubble cheap loans encourage
people to buy more and bigger homes
housing prices began to rise by 10% a
year so many took out a second mortgage
on their old house to fund consumption
you want to go on this vacation buy some
new clothes how about put an addition on
your house you don't have the money how
about a home equity loan that's for you
just use your house is a piggy bank the
bank's granted loans to almost anyone
why would you need a decent income to
buy a home if you can get rich just
living in it the market even coined the
term Nina loans no income no assets no
problem you'll get alone anyway the
legislation was more aggressively
pushing lenders to lend the people of
modest means people with whose incomes
were 80% of the median income or below
politicians encouraged this for a long
time both the left and the right have
been encouraging homeownership so
they've created deductions subsidies and
insurances and they created two huge
mortgage financing companies Fannie Mae
and Freddie Mac their job was to use
thousands of billions of dollars to
insure loans for people who couldn't get
them from the open market
they were government-sponsored
enterprises they had private owners but
they had been created by Congress can
their transactions were guaranteed by
the government
[Music]
so particularly Fannie Mae and Freddie
Mac are government-sponsored enterprises
and what it means is they're private not
now maybe but but they're private
companies that have special charters
from the government and the thing about
government-sponsored enterprises which
is the main thing people are talking
about is a sense that they're guaranteed
by the government
first of all government-sponsored
corporations that help create our
mortgage system I introduced two of the
leaders here today they call those
people Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac as
well as the Federal Home Loan Banks will
increase their commitment to minority
markets by more than four hundred and
forty billion dollars in the last decade
Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac have donated
more than two hundred million dollars to
politicians in Washington Enterprise
sponsored government I asked the forum
of Freddie Mac chief economist what they
got for their money I don't know I mean
I uh that's a that's a tougher question
now they they had they had a pretty good
charter they they were regulated in a
spotty way in many ways the regulatory
structure wasn't that bad but it was the
case that that the regular regulatory
structure was a compromise it wasn't a
Treasury it wasn't it housing really it
was some somewhere in between no there
was a huge moral hazard courtesy of the
government in the mortgage market when
the government through Fannie and
Freddie started to guarantee mortgages
then the lenders were no longer worried
about getting their money back because
the government said we guarantee it and
so that's why I proposed I urged
Congress to fully fund the American
dream downpayment fund this will use
money taxpayers money
to help a qualified low-income buyer
make a down payment
well greed has to be balanced with a
certain amount of fear and that's what
down payment rules are all about an
amortization rule
is to keep people from carried away by
as you say the greed of expecting to
become rich by buying a home and
reselling at a higher price and that's
important if a one of the barriers to
home ownership is the inability to make
a down payment and if one of the goals
is to increase home ownership it makes
sense to help people pay that down
payment this is the problem
the moral hazard we gave a moral hazard
to home buyers once you say that you can
buy a home with no no down payment all
of a sudden there's no risk to the
borrower he doesn't care if he overpays
because if the house keeps going up he
makes money if it stops going up the
bank loses the money you know we have
moral hazards in our banking system the
US government guarantees all bank
deposits well what does that mean that
means that depositors don't care what
the banks do with their money once they
deposit it because they know the
government guarantees it and the federal
government obviously has to play an
important role and we will we will I
mean when I lay out a goal I mean it why
are they doing that why can't we let
mortgages to be financed in the private
sector the reason is because the private
sector would not finance these crazy
mortgages and real estate prices would
have to come down to levels that people
can actually afford
how could you promote home ownership if
people can't afford a home the big banks
dared to make riskier loans because they
had started repackaging loans and
selling them to others and securities
they sold them to each other to Fannie
Mae and Freddie Mac and they sold them
to Norway to Germany and to China if the
loans turned bad someone else would end
up with a hot potato
I guess we're a little early what do you
want to do anything but inspect this
temple of capitalism
look at their eyes popping out of the
head drooling over the very things that
are taking away their jobs now don't get
all excited my family think that America
is a pretty swell place and I don't want
you to disillusion I know everybody
wanted to buy because the ranking
agencies that great securities gave the
mortgage-backed bonds their highest
rating they promised huge payoffs at
near zero risk the rating agencies
thought that house prices would just
keep rising and then there was that
minor detail that the rating agencies
were being paid by the sillas of the
securities so I think the process was
corrupted first of all the government
licenses Moody's and Standard & Poor's
so there's only a few companies who are
authorized to rate these bonds so it
wasn't really a free market the
government was in bed with with Moody's
and with Standard & Poor's but also you
had this perverse relationship between
Wall Street and the rating agencies
where they were paying the rating
agencies to rate the products that they
were structuring and so there was no
this was an incestuous relationship
where they knew if they put bad ratings
on them they wouldn't sell and they
didn't sell they wouldn't be making all
this money constantly rating them
they were great days but it was all
based on a market on steroids loans were
cheap enough to keep driving housing
prices up but when interest rates return
to normal levels in 2006 the spell was
broken but for one person the future was
still bright Ben Bernanke Alan Greenspan
successor as federal research and tell
me what is the worst-case scenario if in
fact we were to see prices come down
substantially across the country well I
guess I don't buy your premise it's a
pretty unlikely possibility we've never
had a decline in house prices at a
nationwide nationwide basis people could
no longer get new loans to pay off the
old ones those who had been given a
mortgage despite a very low income
couldn't afford to stay the prices
started falling making the mortgage
backed securities increasingly worthless
there's not much indication at this
point that subprime mortgage issues have
spread into the broader mortgage market
which still seems to be healthy the
rating agencies removed the high ratings
from the securities investors who never
looked beyond the ratings suddenly
didn't know what they had booked they
didn't know how risky those loans were
overall the US economy appears likely to
expand at a moderate pace over the
second half of 2007 with growth then
strengthening a bit in 2008 to a rate
close to the economy's underlying trends
the dominoes started falling investors
stopped buying mortgage-backed
securities and refused to lend to those
who depended on them investment banks
like Bear Stearns and Lehman Brothers
suddenly couldn't get new loans to stay
in business Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac
could no longer hide the disaster the
financial crisis started in a way that
is eerily similar to today's situation
it started with an economic crisis in
the US and a government that responded
decisively after 9/11 and the dot-com
collapse the US government decided to
save the economy by inflating plane
bubble
today the world is trying to get out of
the financial crisis by inflating a new
bubble the difference is that this
bubble is much bigger
after they did the dot-com bubble and
that first and they reinflates take
credit crisis bubble and though in that
first now they've created the bubble of
all bubbles it's not only the United
States this is a global bubble they're
all into it it's called a bailout bubble
hey the economy's going down
recession setting in sales don't look
good exports soft need more money how
about we'll call it stimulus packages
and from Australia to the United States
from the UK to China it dumped in money
money into the system to keep it going
in September of 2008 the US economy is
near collapse Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac
have been taken over by the government
on September 15 giant investment bank
Lehman Brothers goes bankrupt after
monumental bets on real estate AIG the
largest insurance company in the world
collapses the next day fear sets in it
seems like anyone can fail suddenly
banks no longer dare make loans to
companies or each other experts warn
that the economy is about to collapse
there's CBS News special report
a presidential address to the nation
from CBS News headquarters in New York
here is Katie Couric good evening
everyone President Bush asked the
network's for this television time so he
could talk directly to you about a
national crisis some of this country's
major financial institutions are in
danger of collapsing under the weight of
bad mortgages and that would be
devastating for the entire economy we
are in the midst of a serious financial
crisis and the federal government is
responding with decisive action in a
televised speech Bush scares the market
even more while still claim that they
can trust him he has a solution under
our proposal the federal government
would put up to 700 billion taxpayer
dollars on the line to purchase troubled
assets that are clogging the financial
system the US government wants to spend
huge amount on Wall Street banks to
cover their bad deals even banks who
don't want the money we'd be forced to
take it so that the public won't know
which banks are on the brink of collapse
Oh favor say aye
I want to thank Secretary of Treasury
for working hard with the members thank
the members for working long hours like
they've been doing to come up with a
solution that's bipartisan and that will
solve the problem on October 3rd
Congress approves the biggest financial
bailout in history 700 million dollars
around the world in Germany Italy Canada
South Korea and Great Britain other
politicians do the same to save their
thanks thanks thanks we've taken the
right the decisive in the tough decision
that was necessary to protect the
stability of the financial system and to
protect the depositors David Walker was
you as Controller General from 1998 to
2008 he quit because he was so worried
about the US economy that he wanted to
have the freedom to warn about what may
happen in my view the bailout was
necessary in certain regards but in many
cases we wasted a lot of money because
we didn't do three things
first have clearly defined objectives
about what we were trying to achieve
secondly have criteria established
upfront as to who would get the money
and who wouldn't get the money and
number three have conditions established
upfront as to what they could and
couldn't do with the money and as a
result of not having those three things
some people got the money that didn't
deserve it other people got the money
that didn't make good use of it
and as a result we had a lot of waste
with regard to taxpayer money what would
it mean if the domestic industry are
allowed to fail you heard senator
Stabenow so I won't repeat other than to
say as a result of the crisis the
situation for the US auto industry
become critical on November 19th they're
CEOs fly to Washington to demand money
the executives came out and they said if
you if you don't do this we are going to
see a jobs Holocaust they issued
extremely high estimates of how many
jobs would be lost but included counting
every single company that supplies them
with anything that's why this is all
about a lot more than just Detroit it's
about saving the US US economy from a
catastrophic collapse
a month later President Bush gives
billions of dollars to General Motors
and Chrysler the money comes from the
bailout package that was really only
designed to save the financial industry
some US auto executives say that their
companies are nearing collapse and that
the only way they can buy time to
restructure is with help from the
federal government Megan McArdle is a
financial analyst for the Atlantic and
it's written extensively about the
problems of the US auto industry
Congress wanted an excuse to bail out
the auto workers and the executives gave
them just enough political cover to say
ah well I'm not really doing this
because I want auto worker votes and I'm
going to give them a huge amount of
money I'm really doing this for the
American economy but if you look at how
much money we gave them you're talking
about almost a hundred billion dollars
is how much we will end up spending on
this you know even if you were saving
millions of jobs it would have been
cheaper to give every single one of
those people $100,000 to go out and find
a new job the big guys on Wall Street
they can't take their losses their
crybaby capitalists oh they preach
capitalism for everybody but themselves
[Music]
the Federal Reserve has cut its key
interest rate to the lowest level on
record Fed Chairman Ben Bernanke and his
colleagues also pledged to use all
available tools to contain the widening
crisis and a longest recession in a
quarter century December 16 2008 it is
time again to pour alcohol into the
punch bowl the Federal Reserve reduces
interest rates to practically zero to
restore investor confidence other
central banks do the same
hey have no credit don't worry about it
just sign on a dotted line let's go in
the housing bubble that they inflated
blew up with all the carnage and all the
bankruptcies and now what is their
solution well gee let's do the same
thing we did before
instead of having interest rates at 1%
let's have them at zero and let's buy
everything we can let's print money and
buy mortgages let's buy credit card debt
student loans
let's buy bonds and let's drop money
from helicopters to try to get the same
risk-taking excessive gambling on Wall
Street let's try to convince Americans
who are already loaded up on debt to go
out and buy more stuff to go on go
deeper into debt and if the banks don't
want to lend the money let's make them
lend the money I mean this is this is
economic you know suicide while the Fed
lowers interest rates president-elect
Barack Obama prepares an enormous
stimulus package meant to get the US
economy going we are running out of the
traditional ammunition that's used in a
recession which is to lower interest
rates they're getting to be about as low
as they can go
the American Recovery and Reinvestment
Act that I will sign today a plan that
meets the principles I laid out in
January is the most sweeping economic
recovery package in our history On
February 7th 2009 Obama approves a
stimulus package worth 787 billion
dollars with a Bush stimulus package
from the year before u.s. politicians
have now spent close to 1 trillion
dollars to stimulate the US economy the
money is spent on roads airports
education unemployment and other
benefits there's a pre are seen
everywhere and you know in Italy dish to
see them from when you ever a jar of
honey you lick your fingers the town of
Union is located a few hours from the
Canadian border this is where the
computer company IBM got it stopped and
grew to be the biggest in the world the
factories are now empty but the town has
acquired a small-town rhythm so there
was surprised when $600,000 from the
stimulus package arrived to combat
homelessness you know on occasion you
know our police officers may run a car
run across someone and and they try to
you know take the person to to an area
where the individual get some shelter
and get something to eat but it's not a
problem here
this is Rodeo Drive in Beverly Hills
probably the world's most famous upscale
shopping district it was here for
example the Julia Roberts went shopping
and pretty woman stimulus money has made
its way here as well these streets are
to be repaved
to the tune of 1 million dollars sure
there are potholes in the asphalt but
it's this really the economy that needs
to be stimulated we had a seven hundred
and eighty seven billion dollar stimulus
go but only about one third of it was
truly stimulus by that I mean timely
targeted and temporary the other two
thirds were things that people wanted to
do have been wanting to do for a long
time but they didn't want to have to pay
for it they wanted to do it as part of
emergency legislation and charge it to
the national credit card the Johnstown
Pennsylvania Airport has three scheduled
flights a day other than that it's quite
empty
we had the flights coming that's when
the people are here right other than
that there's everything but one face is
everywhere Congressman John Murtha the
airport's namesake he's been called the
king of pork and has gotten 200 million
dollars from Earth Airport from
Washington earlier this year the airport
got a new source of revenue $800,000
from the stimulus package to repave this
backup landing strip the head of the
airport insists that the landing strip
is safe so why does it need doing if
it's not a safety issue
because of the steps we take this plant
is about to shift into high gear
one of the biggest stimulus programs was
aimed at the auto industry cash for
clunkers turning your old car and get
cash toward a new one from the
government it was so clear that it's 1
billion dollar budget ran out in a week
so more money was quickly injected many
countries offered similar programs
Germany had the biggest ones and handed
out almost 7 billion dollars to those
who scrapped any car more than 9 years
old while buying a new one our
governments seem to think that German
auto industry is so important we have to
support it in some ways and therefore
they created this bonus they couldn't
call it a scrapping bonus because I
think they knew just how ridiculous that
was so they called it a environment
bonus Karin horn is a doctor of
economics at a German economics
Institute and of course people took
advantage of that it worked as long as
it was on the program worked but now
it's out it's over and of course numbers
are dropping people are feeling that
they ran into additional debt due to
that bonus that they wanted to take
advantage of and they're having problems
they didn't anticipate so Germany spent
almost seven billion dollars to scrap
fully-functioning cars and to maintain
excessive auto factory output once the
program ended the industry was right
back in the dog groups I was just very
surprised that people would accept the
idea so readily that they would accept
the money something else
who wouldn't but that they would find
this a solution that they deemed viable
it doesn't give me a very good
impression of the rationality of the
voter and taxpayers I must say and
that's where we are I think at this
point the problem is now so big that
government stimulus is not going to you
know buy us another five or six years of
phony growth like it did last time
because we have to accumulate so much
more debt now because the bigger the
problem gets the more we have to
stimulate to get that short-term boost
but now the bigger the bust because now
we have a bigger stimulus you know to
get out of the economy about a year
after the worst economic crisis in
modern history Lehman Brothers is gone
but apart from that Wall Street looks
much the same many banks are reporting
record profits the world stock markets
have skyrocketed the market is finally
breathing a sigh of relief but isn't it
somewhat uncomfortable haven't we been
here before all the mayors that we have
taken to save the economy the low
interest rates the massive debt the
safety net of the financial industry
these are the very things that led us
into a crisis in the first place we've
been saved from the consequences of one
burst bubble by inflating a hundred new
ones all over the world
[Music]
one year ago I took office amid two wars
an economy rocked by a severe recession
a financial system on the verge of
collapse and a government deeply in debt
experts from across the political
spectrum warned that if we did not act
we might face a second depression so we
acted immediately and aggressively and
one year later the worst of the storm
has passed to repeal it clearly cities
ever tell the moon
[Music]
there are positive signs this is the
Hamptons outside new you a classic
playground for Manhattan's elite
a house by the Atlantic like this one
costs thirty million dollars and a hot
dog bun
with lobster salad costs $18 fast food
Hampton style the crisis has made its
mark here too there are fewer private
jets at the airport instead the Porsches
jostle the Mercedes on the Turnpike
to New York
[Music]
New York City Washington DC and Los
Angeles California don't represent the
real world they also don't represent the
real part of America the so-called Main
Street of America
my sex money go to Beverly Hill well
there's a lot of money in Berry Hill
I don't think they needed my money
that's a different world that's not the
reality you know done day if you ever
visit Union and need a haircut you may
well end up at Frank Petraeus barber
shop
[Music]
but unfortunately people lost their
homes because it lost their jobs and
it's a they now live another life that
one time we're able to do it a lot of
young people specially educated they try
to move go out of town but I believe in
no matter where they go the situation's
the same a lot where they're gonna go
Detroit now let's return
I wasn't want to tell you this but
you're the reason we came here all the
way from Indiana you've heard all the
talkers now I'm going to show you the
doers the US government has launched
bailouts stimulus packages and
guarantees to the tune of 10,000 billion
dollars caught myself wondering for the
hundredth time how the hell I got here
what the hell I'm doing here
that's more than the total cost to the
US government for World War 1 World War
two the Korean War the Vietnam War the
invasion of Iraq the New Deal the
Marshall Plan and the moon landing by
Ameri Bush almost racked up more US debt
than all presidents before him combined
from George Washington to Bill Clinton
and Obama is almost creating greater
debt than all presidents before him
including george w bush but it's not
just the u.s. that's increasingly
looking like a house of cards during the
crisis many governments went deeply into
debt estimates say that the average debt
in the richest nations will exceed 100
percent by the year 2011
these are loans taken at currently low
interest rates should the interest rate
rise by one percent the u.s. interest
payments will rise by one hundred
billion dollars per year that's more
than the annual cost for the Vietnam
rule sometimes it's just an engine
failure other times it's the deadly flag
if the pilots lucky to flag kill them
and usually he isn't he burns to death
as his plane spins in it sounds absurd
to even think that the United States the
world's economic superpower might crash
after all they get the highest ratings
from the credit rating agencies one of
the lessons that we must learn from the
mortgage way of subprime is you have to
take credit ratings with a big grain
assault because as we saw with the
mortgage-related securities they went
from triple-a rating to junk bond pretty
fast once people understood the true
situation today the United States is
rated triple-a but if it doesn't start
taking steps to put its financial house
in order that triple-a rating will be
lost it's only a matter when and how
quickly in September 2008 the bankruptcy
a one large investment bank billed the
world economy to its knees
the fate of Lehman Brothers raised the
question who was next in line
so everyone avoided doing business with
banks how will the world react if the
next entity to declare bankruptcy is a
nation who is next in line if that were
to happen
some houses of cards have already
started falling this is Iceland until
recently one of the richest nations in
the world when the crisis hits the
Icelandic banks collapsed the Icelandic
stock market crashed
leaving the debt with a small population
for the first time in 50 years this
peaceful country saw riots this is
Greece fear deficits have hit a record
high the national debt is approaching
one hundred and thirty five percent of
GDP the market wants higher interest
rates for Greek loans increasing the
pressure on its drained economy it seems
like the Greek government needs a
bailout to avoid collapse Italy Spain
Portugal and Great Britain are other EU
nations with similar problems what about
my country Sweden the country's finances
are fairly robust our national debts and
deficit are lower than that of most
nations but Sweden is highly dependent
on the world economy more than half of
our prosperity is based on exports when
other countries crash we get hit almost
as hard and Swedish housing prices have
risen during the crisis despite the
recession and despite rising
unemployment but because of low interest
rates and a government mortgage company
SBA be making loans easier to get Swedes
have never carried more debt in relation
to their income doesn't all of this
sound very familiar we have new bubble
February so I am pretty worried about
what's going to happen if you don't want
bubbles to burst then don't blow them up
in the first place because all bubbles
burst if enough things can go wrong some
of them probably will the question is
just which needle will burst this bubble
will it be new credit losses as banks
take on greater risks knowing that the
government considers them too big to
fail we're falling stock prices as
interest rates rise and the steroids
wear off
will it be the Chinese economy
overeating or will it be a collapse of
confidence in the u.s. dollar if we lose
the confidence of our foreign lenders
and we must not allow that to happen but
if that were to happen then it would be
a dramatic decline the dollar a dramatic
increase in interest rates significant
fueling of inflation a very very deep
recession and possibly depression that
would be felt around the world we must
not allow that to happen when the next
bubble bursts you cannot use the same
emergency measures you can't lower
interest rates that are already at rock
bottom
you can't stimulate the economy with
borrowed money if an excessive national
debt is the course of the crisis the
government's could save the banks but
who can save the government's ultimately
there is going to be a price all around
the world to be paid for this and the
longer it continues the bigger that
price is going to be you know this
really is a moral question I mean I can
give you plenty of big and bad numbers
you know when you talk about tens of
trillions of dollars it's just hard to
imagine but you have to put a face on it
and to may I put my children's and my
grandchildren's face on it it's their
future that we're mortgaging when we
tell people that there's going to be a
bailout bubble and they see the world
equity markets up 50 60 % they don't
want to believe it it's another bubble
they want to step right up back to that
table and throw their Dyson try to win
their hand at the wheel of fortune at
Wall Street spinning so people still
don't want to believe that the worst is
yet to come
it's easy to think of these predictions
as much to bloom but that is exactly
what people said the last time when
these experts predicted the 2008
financial crisis they will ask that in
the media to the for real
[Music]
we can do it but we need to do it soon
because the clock is ticking and time is
not working in our favor
[Applause]
[Music]
son of the town folks said he was dumber
than dirt but it didn't bother him he
had a stink eye look in his eyes were
told a different story here's to him
through and as mine was as wide open as
that prairie he left behind his only
weaknesses were women and flower
[Music]
you